you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan W. Anderson.
J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England.
For the past 40 years, he
has been speaking in the United States,
Europe, India, Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's work,
he repudiated all connections
with organized religions and ideologies
and said that his only concern
was to set men absolutely unconditionally free.
He is the author of many books, among them
The Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency of Change,
Freedom from the Known, and The Flight of the Eagle.
This is one of a series of
dialogues between Krishnamurti and Dr. Alan W. Anderson,
who is professor of religious studies at San Diego,
San Diego State University, where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the oracular tradition.
Dr. Anderson, a published poet, received his degree
from Columbia University and the Union Theological Seminary.
He has been honored with a Distinguished
Teaching Award from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, in our
previous conversation, I was extremely
delighted, for myself at least,
that we had made the distinction in
terms of the relation between knowledge and
self-transformation between,
on the one hand,
the relationship that I sustained to the world, as
the world is me and I am the world,
and on the other hand, this dysfunctional condition,
which indicates in your phrase
that a person's
a person is involved in thinking
that the description is the described.
It would appear then that something must be done
to bring about a change in the individual,
and going back to our use of the word individual,
we could say, and you used the word
earlier, that we are dealing with an observer.
So if the individual is not
to make the mistake
of taking the description for the described,
then he must, as an observer,
relate to the observed in a
particular way that is totally different
from the way he has been in his confusion.
I thought perhaps in this
particular conversation, if we pursued that,
it would be a link directly
with what we had said prior.
What we said previously, wasn't it, that
there must be a quality of freedom
from the known,
otherwise the known is merely the repetitive of the past,
the tradition, the image and so on.
The past, surely, sir, is the observer.
Yes.
The past is the accumulated knowledge,
as the me and the we, they and us,
the observer is put together by thought as the past.
Thought is the past.
Thought is never free.
Thought is never new,
because thought is the response of the past
as knowledge, as experience, as memory.
Yes, I follow that.
And the observer, when he observes,
is observing with the memories, experiences, knowledge,
hurts, despairs, hopes, all that, with all that,
and that is the background he looks at the observed.
So, the observer then becomes separate from the observed.
Is the observer different from the observed,
which we'll go into presently later on?
Yes, right.
That leads to all kinds of other things.
So,
when we are talking of freedom from the known,
we are talking about the freedom from the observer.
The observer, yes.
And the observer is
the tradition, the past,
the conditioned mind that looks at things,
looks at itself, looks at the world,
looks at me and so on.
So, the observer is always dividing.
The observer is the past,
and therefore he cannot observe wholly.
If a person uses the first person pronoun,
I,
while he is taking the description for the described,
this is the observer he
refers to when he says, I.
Yes.
Yes, please do go on.
I is the past.
I see.
I is the whole structure of what has been.
The remembrances, the memories, the hurts,
the various demands,
all that is put together,
is the past.
In the world, the I,
who is the observer.
And therefore, division.
The observer and the observed.
The observer who thinks he is a Christian
and observes a non-Christian or a communist,
is this division,
this attitude of mind which
observes
with a conditioned responses,
with memories and so on.
So, that is the known.
下一次
I mean, I think that is logically so.
Oh no, it follows precisely from what you've said.
Yes. So, we are asking, can the mind,
or the whole structure,
can the mind be free from the known?
Otherwise the repetitious action,
repetitious attitudes, repetitious ideologies will go on,
modified, changed, but in the same direction.
So...
Oh, go ahead. I was just going to say something,
but I think I'll let it
wait until you finish what you've said.
Yes. So, what is this freedom from the known?
I think that's very important to understand,
because any creative action
– I'm using the word creative in its original sense,
not in the sense creative writing, creative...
I know what you're...
...bakery, creative essay, creative pictures,
I'm not talking in those sense.
In the deeper sense of that word,
creative means something totally new being born.
I mean, it's not creative, it's merely repetitive, modified.
Changed, what the past.
So, unless there is a freedom from the known,
there is no creative action at all.
Which is, freedom implies not the negation of the known,
but the understanding of the known,
and that understanding brings about
an intelligence which is the very essence of freedom.
Right. I'd like to make sure
that I've understood your use of this word, creative.
Yes, that's why I...
It seems to me very, very important.
Yes.
People who use the word creative
in the sense that you described,
creative this, that and the other...
That's a horror.
That is the dreadful way of using that word.
Because what the issue is of their activity,
is something merely novel.
Novel, novel. That's right.
Not radically new, but novel.
It's like creative writing, teaching creative writing.
It's so absurd.
Exactly. Yes.
Now I do, I think, grasp precisely
the distinction that you've made.
And I must say I fully agree with that.
Unless you feel new, you can't create anything new.
That's right.
And the person who imagines that he is creative
in this other sense that we pointed to,
is a person whose reference for his activity
is this observer that we mentioned,
that is tied to the past.
Yes, that's right.
So even if something does appear that is really
extraordinarily novel, merely,
Yes.
but still extraordinarily novel,
they are kidding themselves.
The novel is not the creative.
Exactly.
The novel is just the novel.
Right. And today especially, it
seems to me, in our culture,
we've become hysterical about this,
because in order to be creative,
one simply must rack his brains
in order to produce something which in itself
is bizarre enough to get attention.
That's right. Attention, success.
Yes.
It has to be novel to the degree
that I feel knocked on the head by it.
Yes, eccentric and all the rest of it.
Exactly. But if that tension is increased,
then with each succeeding generation,
the person is put to tremendous stress,
not to repeat the past, which he can't help repeating.
Repeating, quite. That's why I say,
Exactly.
freedom is one thing and knowledge is another.
We must relate the two and see whether the mind
can be free from knowledge.
We won't go into it now.
This is real meditation for me.
You follow, sir? Yes, I do.
Because when we talk about meditation,
we'll go into it, but...
You see, whether the brain can record
and be free not to record.
The brain to record and operate when necessary
in the recording, in memory, in knowledge,
and be free to observe without the observer.
You see?
Oh, yes, yes, I see.
That distinction seems to me absolutely necessary.
Otherwise it wouldn't be intelligible.
No.
No, yes.
So, knowledge means, is necessary to act,
in the sense, my going home
from here to the place I live.
I must have knowledge.
I must have knowledge to speak English.
I must have knowledge to
write a letter and so on.
Everything.
The knowledge as function
is mechanical function is necessary.
Now, if I use that
knowledge in my relationship with you,
another human being,
I am bringing about a barrier,
a division between you and me,
who is the observer.
If I am making myself clear.
And I am the observed in that case.
Yes.
Right, in that context.
That is, knowledge in relationship,
in human relationship, is destructive.
That is, knowledge,
which is the tradition, the memory, the image,
which the mind has built about you,
when we are related together,
that knowledge is separating.
And therefore creates conflict in that relationship.
As we said earlier, where there is division,
there must be conflict.
Division between India and Pakistan,
India and America, Russia and all that,
this divisive activity,
politically, religiously, economically, socially,
in every way, must inevitably bring conflict,
and therefore violence.
That is obvious.
Exactly.
Now, when in relationship,
in human relationship,
knowledge comes between,
then in that relationship there must be conflict.
Between a wife, husband and wife, boy and girl,
wherever there is the operation of,
the observer who is the past, who is knowledge,
in that activity there is division,
and therefore conflict in relationship.
So now the question that comes up next
is the one of freedom from being subject
to this repetitive round.
That's right.
Good.
Now, is that possible? You follow, sir?
It's an immense question because
human beings live in relationship.
Yes.
There is no life without relationship.
Life means to be related.
Exactly.
People who retire into a monastery and all that,
they are still related,
however much they might like to think they are alone,
they are actually related.
Yes.
Related to the past.
Oh yes, very much so.
To their saviour, to their Christ,
to their Buddha, to their...
You follow? All that, they are related to the past.
And their rule.
And their rule is everywhere.
They live in the past.
And therefore they are the most destructive people,
because they are not creative in
the deeper sense of that word.
No, and they also,
insofar as they are involved in this confusion
that you have been talking about,
are not even producing anything novel.
Not that that means anything,
but perhaps that would rather radically...
The novel would be for a man who is talkative
to enter a monastery where they don't talk.
That's a novel to him,
and he said that's a miracle.
Right.
So, our problem then is,
what place has knowledge in human relationship?
Yes, that's the problem.
That's one problem.
Yes.
Because relationship with human beings
is the highest importance, obviously.
Because out of that relationship
we create the society in which we live.
Out of that relationship all our existence comes.
This would take us back again to the earlier statement,
I am the world and the world is me.
Yes, sir.
That is a statement about relationship.
It's a statement about many other things too.
Of course.
But that is a statement about relationship.
The statement, the description is not the described,
is the statement of the rupture
of the relationship.
That's right.
In terms of everyday activity.
Sir, everyday activity is my life, is our life.
Is everything. Yes, precisely.
Whether I go to the office, factory,
or drive a bus, or whatever it is,
it is life, living.
But it is interesting, isn't it,
that even when that rupture is undergone
at a very destructive level,
what we've called thought,
in the context of our description of it and image,
becomes itself, even distorted.
Of course.
So that the distortion that we've been calling knowledge,
in terms of its application,
not what you described as
I need to know how
to get from here to there.
No, of course.
Can itself suffer an even worse condition
than we are presently related to?
And we have tomes upon tomes
about that pathology in itself, don't we?
Yes, please do go on.
So, knowledge and freedom.
They must both exist together.
Not freedom and knowledge.
It's the harmony between the two.
The two operating all the time in relationship.
The knowledge and the freedom.
Freedom.
In harmony.
It's like they can never be divorced.
If I want to live with you in great harmony,
which is love,
which we will discuss that later on,
there must be this absolute sense of freedom from you,
not dependency and so on, so on, so on.
This absolute sense of freedom,
and operating at the same
time in the field of knowledge.
Exactly.
So somehow this knowledge,
if I may use a theological word here
without prejudicing what we are talking about,
if in correct relationship
with this freedom,
is somehow continuously redeemed.
It is somehow operating no longer destructively,
but in coordination with the freedom
in which I may live,
because we haven't got to that freedom yet.
No, that's why we have somewhat analysed
or discussed or opened the question of knowledge.
Yes.
And we haven't gone into the question of freedom,
what it means.
No, but we have established something, I think,
that this conversation so far has revealed,
which is terribly important,
at least I'd say for my students,
in terms of helping them
not to misunderstand what you are saying.
Quite.
I have the feeling that many persons,
if they are not sufficiently attentive to what you say,
simply dismiss many statements you say out of hand as...
Impossible.
...as either impossible,
or if they like the aesthetics of it,
it still doesn't apply to them.
It's a lovely thing out there.
Wouldn't it be great if somehow we could do this?
Yes, quite.
But you see, you haven't said that.
You haven't said what they think you've said.
You've said something about knowledge,
with respect to pathology,
and you've said something about knowledge,
in which knowledge itself is no longer destructive.
No.
So we are not saying that
knowledge as such is the bad guy,
and something else is the good guy.
No.
No, I think it's terribly important that that's seen.
Yes, that's what I...
I wouldn't mind it being repeated over and over again.
Quite, quite.
Because I do heartily feel
that it's easy to misunderstand it here.
You see, sir, that's very important because religion,
at least the meaning of that word,
is to gather together to be attentive.
That is the true meaning of that word, religion.
I've looked it up...
Oh, yes, I agree.
Gathering together all energy to be attentive.
Yes, to be attentive.
Otherwise it's not religion.
Religion is all the thing...
So, we'll discuss that when you come to it.
So, freedom means the sense of complete austerity
and sense of total negation of the observer.
Exactly.
Out of that comes
ignorance, austerity, everything else.
We'll go into that later on.
But austerity in itself doesn't produce it.
No.
We've turned that upside down.
Right.
Austere means, really, the word itself means ash.
Yes.
Dry, brittle.
But the austerity of which we're talking about
is something entirely different.
It is the freedom
of this austerity, inwardly.
There's a beautiful biblical phrase that points to this.
Just three words, beauty for ashes.
When a transformation takes place.
And in English we have
the phrase, ashes in the mouth.
When the whole thing has come to the earth.
Come, ashes in the mouth.
But there's the change from ashes to beauty.
So, freedom in action in the field of knowledge.
And in the field of human relationship.
Because that is the highest importance, human relationship.
Oh yes, yes.
Oh yes, particularly if I am
the world and the world is me.
Obviously.
Yes.
So, what place has knowledge in human relationship?
Knowledge in the sense, past experience, tradition, image.
Yes.
What has the observer, who is the observer,
all that is the observer,
what place has the observer in human relationship?
What place has knowledge, on the one hand,
what place has the observer?
Observer is the knowledge.
Is the knowledge.
But there's the possibility of seeing knowledge,
not simply negatively,
but in coordination, in true creative relationship.
I said that.
Exactly.
That is, I am related to you.
Let's... to make it very simple.
I am related to you.
You are my brother, or whatever it is,
husband, wife, whatever it is.
And what place has knowledge as the observer,
which is the past, and knowledge is the past,
what place has that in our relationship?
If our relationship is creative, in the sense...
And it is not.
Not if.
We must take it actually as it is.
I am related to you, I am married to you,
I am your wife or husband, whatever it is.
Now, what is the actuality in that relationship?
The actuality, not theoretical actuality,
but the actuality is that I am separate from you.
The actuality must be that we are not divided.
We are.
I may call you my husband, my wife,
but I am concerned with my success,
I am concerned with my money,
I am concerned with my ambitions, my envy,
I am full of me.
Yes, I see that.
But I want to make sure now that
we haven't reached a confusion here.
Yes, we have.
When I say that the actuality
is that we are not separate,
I don't mean to say that at the phenomenal level
that a dysfunction is occurring.
I am fully aware of that.
But if we are going to
say that the world is me
and I am the world...
Ah, we say it theoretically, we don't feel it.
Precisely.
But if that is the
case, that the world is me
and I am the world...
And this is actual. This is actual.
This is actual only when
I have no division in myself.
Exactly.
But I have a division.
If I have a division...
And therefore it is just...
...then there is no relationship between one and the other.
Therefore, one accepts the idea
that the world is me and
the world, me is the world.
That is just an idea.
Look, sir...
Yes, I understand, but if and when it happens...
No, wait. Just see what takes place in my mind,
what takes place in my mind.
I make a statement of that kind,
the world is you and you are the world.
The mind then translates it into an idea,
into a concept,
and tries to live according to that concept.
Exactly.
It has abstracted from reality.
This is knowledge in the destructive sense.
That is what is going on.
I won't call it destructive or positive.
This is what is going on.
Well, let's say the issue from it is hell.
Yes, yes.
So, in my relationship with you,
what place has knowledge, the past, the image,
which is the observer, all that is the observer,
what place has the observer in our relationship?
Actually, the observer is the factor of division.
Right.
And therefore, the conflict between you and me,
this is what is going
on in the world, every day.
Then one would have to say, it seems to me,
following the conversation,
point by point,
that the place of this observer,
understood as you have pointed it out,
is the point of this relationship.
It is the point where there is really, actually,
no relationship at all.
I may sleep with my wife, or you may sleep,
and so on, so on,
but actually there is no relationship.
Uh-huh.
Because I have my own pursuits, my own ambitions,
all the idiosyncrasies, and so on,
and she has hers.
So we are always separate.
And therefore always in battle with each other.
Which means the observer as the past
is the factor of division.
Yes.
I was just wanting to be sure that the phrase,
is the place,
what is the place of the observer,
was understood in the context of what we are saying.
We have made the statement
that there is such a thing.
Yes.
Well, its place as such would seem to me
not to be what we usually
mean by its occupying a place.
Yes.
We are talking rather about an activity here
that is profoundly disordered.
Sir, as long as there is the observer,
there must be conflict in relationship.
Yes, I follow that.
Wait, wait.
No, see what happens.
I make a statement of that kind.
Someone will translate into an idea,
into a concept,
and say, how am I to live that concept?
The fact is he doesn't observe himself as the observer.
That's right.
He is the observer looking out there,
making a distinction between himself...
And the statement.
Right, making a division.
Division.
Now, so, has the observer
any place at all in relationship?
I say...
I say no.
The moment he comes into existence,
into relationship, there is no relationship.
The relationship is not...
Is not. That's right.
...is not something that is in dis-relationship.
Yes, that's right.
We are talking about something that
in fact does not even exist.
Exists.
Therefore we have to go into the question
why human beings in their relationship
with other human beings are so violent.
Because that is spreading throughout the world.
I was told the other day in India,
a mother came to see me,
very brahmanical family and very cultured
and all the rest of it.
Her son, who is six,
when she asked him to do something,
he took up a stick and began to hit her.
A thing unknown. You follow, sir?
I mean, the idea that you should hit your mother
is traditionally something incredible.
And this boy did it.
And I said, see what is the fact.
We went into it, she understood, so on.
So, to understand violence, one has to understand violence.
One has to understand division.
The division was already there.
Otherwise he would not have picked up the stick.
Division between nations. You follow, sir?
This race form armaments is
one of the factors of violence,
which is, I am calling myself American,
and others calling himself Russian
or Hindu or whatever it is,
this division is the factor of real violence and hatred.
If a mind... not if a...
When a mind sees that, he
cuts away all division in himself.
He is no longer a Hindu, American, Russian,
he is a human being,
with his problems, which then he is trying to solve,
not in terms of India or America or Russia.
So that's...
So we come to the point,
can the mind be free in the relationship,
which means orderly, not chaotic.
No, no. Orderly.
It has to be, otherwise
you couldn't use the word relation.
No, no. So can the mind be free of that?
Free of the observer.
If not, there is no hope.
That's the whole point.
If not, we've had it.
And all the escapes and going off into other religions,
doing all kinds of tricks, and no meaning.
Now, this demands a great deal of perception, insight,
into the fact of your life,
how one lives one's life.
After all, philosophy means the love of truth,
love of wisdom,
not the love of some abstraction.
Oh, no. Oh, no, no, no.
Wisdom is supremely practical.
Practical. Therefore, here it is.
That is, can a human being live in relationship,
in freedom,
and yet operate in the field of knowledge?
And yet operate in the field of knowledge.
And be absolutely orderly.
Otherwise it's not freedom.
Because order means virtue.
Yes. Yes.
Which doesn't exist in the world at the present time.
There is no sense of virtue in anything.
They will repeat,
virtue is a creative thing,
is a living thing, is a moving thing.
I'm thinking, as you're saying this, about virtue,
which is really power,
which is really the ability to act.
And if I'm following you correctly,
what you're really saying,
and please correct me if I'm way off here,
what you're really saying is that
the ability to act in the strict sense,
which must be creative,
otherwise it's not an action,
but it is simply a reaction.
Yes, a repetition. A repetition.
That the ability to act,
or virtue, as you put it,
bears with it, necessarily,
the implication of order.
It must.
There seems to me no way out of that.
Yes. Yes.
I just wanted to recover that step at a time.
So can I come back?
Yes.
In human relationship as it exists now,
we are looking at that, what actually is.
In that human relationship there is conflict,
sexual violence and so on, so on, so on,
every kind of violence.
Now, can man live at total peace
otherwise it's not creative?
In human relationship,
because that is the basis of all life.
You understand?
I'm very taken with the way you have pursued this.
I notice that when we ask this question,
is it possible that,
the reference for it is always a totality.
Yes.
And the reference over here is a fragment,
or a fragmentation, or a division.
Never once have you said that
the passage from one to the other
is a movement that even exists.
No, it can't exist.
Quite quite. Absolutely.
I think, Mr Krishnamurti, that
nothing is so difficult to grasp.
As this statement that you have made.
From this to that.
Yes.
There is nothing that we are taught from childhood up
to render such a possibility,
a matter, for taking seriously.
Because, well, of course,
one doesn't like to make sweeping statements
about the way everybody has been educated.
But I'm thinking of myself,
from a child upward,
all the way through graduate school,
accumulating a lot of this knowledge
that you have been talking about.
I don't remember anybody saying to me,
you know, you've been pointing me to a literature
that so categorically makes this distinction
between one and the other
as in terms of each other,
not accessible to each other through passage.
No, no, no. Quite, quite.
Now, I'm correct in understanding you, aren't I?
Quite right.
Maybe I could just say this
as an aside.
The fragment can't become the whole.
No, the fragment cannot become the whole,
in and of itself.
But the fragment is always trying to become the whole.
Exactly, exactly.
Now, of course, in the years of very serious
and devoted contemplation and exploration of this,
which quite clearly you have undertaken
with great passion,
I suppose it must have occurred to you
that the first sight of this,
while one is in a condition of the observer,
must be very frightening.
In the condition of the observer,
the thought that there is no passage.
No, but you see, I
never looked at it that way.
But please tell me how you looked at it.
Please.
From childhood I never thought I was a Hindu.
I see.
I never thought when I was educated in England
and all the rest of it, that I was European.
I just, I never was caught in that trap.
I don't know how it happened.
I was never caught in the trap.
When you were quite little then,
and your playmates said to you,
well, now look, you are a Hindu,
what did you say?
I probably put on Hinduism,
you know, all the trappings of Brahman tradition, I was.
But it never penetrated deeply.
As we say in the
vernacular, it never got to you.
It never got to me, that's right.
I see. That's very remarkable.
That is extraordinary.
The vast number of people in the world
seem to have been got to with respect to this.
That's why I think, you see,
propaganda has become the means of change.
Yes, yes.
Propaganda is not truth.
Repetition is not truth.
It's a formality.
It's a form of violence too.
That's just...
Yes.
So, a mind that merely observes,
doesn't react to what it observes,
according to its conditioning,
which means there is no observer at any time,
therefore no division.
It happened to me,
I don't know how it happened, but it's happened.
In observing all this,
I see in every human relationship,
every kind of human relationship,
there is this division and therefore violence.
And to me the very essence of non-relationship
is the factor of me and you.
I was just trying to go
back in my own personal history
and think of when I was a child.
I did, while accepting that I was different,
I did believe that.
I did come to accept that.
There was something else, however,
that always held me very, very hard to center
in terms of making an ultimate issue of that.
And that was an experience I
had when I was rowing a boat.
I spent some time in Scandinavia as a child,
and I used to take the
boat out on the fjord every day.
And when I would row,
I was profoundly moved by the action of the water
when I moved the oar.
Because I lifted the oar out of the water,
and there was a separation in substance
between the water and the oar.
But the water, which was necessary for support
and for purchase, so that I could propel myself,
never lost touch with itself.
It always turned into itself
without ever having left itself in the beginning.
And once in a while I would laugh at myself
and say, if anyone catches you looking at this water
any longer than you are doing,
they will think that you
are clear out of your mind.
This is the observer talking to himself, of course.
But that made such a profound impression on me
that I think it was what you might call
a little salvation for me.
And I never lost that.
So maybe there is some relationship
between that apprehension,
which I think changed my being,
and what it is that you are talking about
as one who never ever suffered
this sense of separation at all.
Yes. Yes. Please go ahead.
So that brings us to the point, sir, doesn't it,
can the human mind,
which has evolved in separation...
Yes.
...in...
...fragmentations...
This is where evolution is. Yes.
...can such a mind transform, undergo,
ええ
regeneration which is not produced by influence,
by propaganda, by threat and punishment.
Because if it changes because it
is going to get a reward...
It hasn't changed. It hasn't changed.
So that is one of the fundamental things
which one has to ask and
answer it in action, not in words.
In action. Action.
Oh, yes, yes.
Which is, my mind, the human mind,
has evolved in contradiction, in duality,
the me and the not-me,
has evolved in this traditional
cleavage, division, fragmentation.
Now, can that mind observe this fact,
observe without the observer,
and only then there is a regeneration?
As long as there is an observer observing this,
then there is a conflict. I
don't know if I am making...
Yes, you do. You make
yourself very clear on two levels.
One is the mind.
So, I made myself clear on two levels.
On the level of discourse alone,
which I know is not your major concern,
on the level of discourse alone it necessarily follows
that it must be the case that this possibility exists,
otherwise we would be talking nonsense.
But then the agony of the situation at large
that we have been describing is simply that
whether this can be done or
no, never occurs to a person,
and in the absence of it even occurring,
the repetition is going to continue indefinitely
and things are going to get worse and worse.
Sir, the difficulty is most people won't even listen.
I am sighing, I know that.
Won't listen. If they do
listen, they listen with their conclusions.
If I am a communist, I will
listen to you up to a point.
After that I won't listen to you.
And if I am slightly demented,
I will listen to you and translate what I hear
according to my...
Dementia.
Exactly.
So, one has to be extraordinarily serious to listen.
Serious in the sense,
put aside my peculiar prejudices and idiosyncrasies
and listen to what you are saying.
Because the listening is the miracle,
not what shall I do with what you have said.
Not what shall I listen to.
But the act of listening.
The act of listening itself. We are back to ING.
The listening itself.
That requires... I mean, you are
good enough to listen to me,
because you want to find out.
But the vast majority of people say,
what are you talking about? I
want to go and enjoy myself.
So go and talk to somebody else.
So,
to create an atmosphere,
to create an ambience, a feeling,
look, life is dreadfully serious, my friend, do listen.
It is your life, don't waste it, do listen.
To bring about a human being that will listen
is of the greatest importance,
because we don't want to listen.
It is too disturbing.
I understand.
I have tried sometimes in
class to make this very point.
And sometimes I suggest that we should watch the animal,
especially the wild animal.
Of course.
Because if it is not listening, it is likely dead.
Dead, yes, sir.
There is this extraordinary,
Attention.
attention that it makes,
and every instant of its life is a crisis.
Ah, absolutely.
And you know what happens?
The eyes out there show in
the main that they are thinking
I am talking about animal psychology.
I am not talking about psychology at all.
I am talking about what is the case,
which is either-or,
and there isn't any way
to get from either to or.
Right.
That's what I mean.
So I think I understand you.
You see, sir, in America what is happening is now,
as I observe it, and I may be mistaken,
they are not serious.
They are playing with new things,
something entertaining,
go from one thing to the other.
And they think this is searching.
Searching.
Yes.
Searching, asking,
but they get trapped in each one of them.
Yes.
And by the end of
it they have nothing but ashes.
So it is becoming more and more difficult
for human beings to be serious,
to listen, to see what they are,
not what they should be.
No, what is the case.
What is.
Exactly.
That means you please do listen for five minutes.
Uh-huh.
In this conversation you are listening,
because you are interested in
it, you want to find out.
But the vast majority of people, they say,
for God's sake, leave me alone,
I have my little house, my wife,
my car, my yacht, or whatever it is,
for God's sake, don't change
anything as long as I live.
You know, going back to
what I do know something about,
namely the academy,
because I am situated there in terms of day-to-day activity,
I have often remarked to myself in attending conferences,
where papers are read, that nobody is listening.
Ah.
Yes.
It's one long monologue,
and after a while you get the feeling
that it really is a shocking waste of time.
Yes.
And then even to sit down and have coffee,
the discussion, say, between classes
usually runs on the basis of babble,
where we are just talking about things
that we are not genuinely interested in,
in order to fill up space.
This, however, is far more serious a matter
than simply a description of what's going on.
So it's a matter of life and death.
Exactly.
If the house is burning, I've got to do something.
Right.
It isn't, I'm going to discuss who burned the house.
No.
What colour his hair was, whether
it was black or white or purple.
I want to put that fire out.
Yes. Or if such and such had not happened,
the house would not have been burned.
The house would not be burned.
I mean, that's all.
Right. I know. I know.
And I feel it's so urgent,
because I see it in India,
I see it in Europe and America,
everywhere I go, this sense of slackness,
sense of despair,
and sense of hopeless activity that's going on.
So to come back to what we were saying,
relationship is the highest importance.
When in that relationship there is conflict,
we produce a society which will further that conflict,
through education, through national sovereignty,
through all the rest of it
that's going on in the world.
So a serious man, serious in
the sense who is really concerned
about the world, is a serious man.
So a serious man, serious in
the sense who is really concerned
about the world, is a serious man.
Committed, must give his total attention
to this question of relationship, freedom and knowledge.
If I've heard you correctly,
and I don't mean by that
words that have passed between us,
but if I have truly heard you,
I've heard something very terrifying,
that this disorder that in part we have described
has a built-in necessity in it.
As long as it persists, it can never change.
It can never change.
Any modification of it is more of the same.
Yes, more of the same. More of the same.
I have the feeling, and
I hope I've understood you correctly,
that there's a relationship between
the starkness of this necessity
and the fact that there cannot be a gradual progress,
or as a philosopher would
put it, something like essential progress.
No, no, no.
But nevertheless there is some demonic progress
that takes place within this disorder
that is not so much a progress
as it is a proliferation of the same.
And necessarily so. Quite.
Isn't that what you've been saying?
Yes. Necessarily so.
You know that word progress,
I was told the other day,
meant entering into enemy's country fully armed.
Really?
おぉ…
Progress is entering into an enemy's country.
Fully armed. Fully armed.
Dear me.
Sir, this is what's happening.
Oh, I know.
Next time we converse, the next time,
I would like very much, if you'd be good enough,
to pursue precisely what we have just come to,
namely this necessity,
and the necessity that produced that statement.
Yes, quite.